Guide to the Alfred Playfair Powelson Sermons, 1883-1888
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Alfred Playfair Powelson Sermons 1883-1888
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Powelson, Alfred Playfair, 1851-1916
0.2 Linear Feet 19 Items
Alfred Playfair Powelson (1851-1916) was a Methodist minister who served in Ohio and in Tacoma, Washington. Powelson founded and served as principal of the non-denominational Tacoma Academy (1889-1898) and later served as president of the College of the City of Tacoma (1898-1905).
Collection includes 18 manuscript sermons of Methodist minister Alfred Playfair Powelson, dated 1883 to 1888. Each sermon is loosely tied with original string and three have printed cover sheets. Some sermons are title with only a book, chapter and verse, while Powelson supplied titles for others. Powelson often recorded the location and date that he preached each sermon. The bulk of the sermons in the collection were given at Woodbury, Conn. or Tacoma, Wash. Also included is Powelson's original minister's license from the State of Ohio, dated 1875.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Alfred Playfair Powelson Sermons were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in March 2011.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
1851 Born July 7 as Alfred Playfair Powelson in Plainfield, Ohio to Valentine Powelson and Ellen Thrapp
1875 Received B.A. from Adrian College
1875-1879 Served as a Methodist Minister in Richwood, Middlebury, and Lebanon, Ohio.
1880 Received M.A. from Adrian College
1882 Received Bachelor of Divinity from Yale
1883-1887 Served as Minister to the 1st Congregational Church in Woodbury, Conn.
1887 Married Laura Elizabeth Bull
1889-1898 Principal and Founder of Tacoma Academy
1892 Daughter Elizabeth born
1896 Received Ph.D. from Adrian College
1897 Son Alfred Playfair Powelson, Jr. born
1898-1905 President of the College of the City of Tacoma
1916 Died on December 16th in Tacoma, Wash.
Collection Overview
Collection includes 18 manuscript sermons of Methodist minister Alfred Playfair Powelson, dated 1883 to 1888. Each sermon is loosely tied with original string and three have printed cover sheets. Some sermons are title with only a book, chapter and verse, while Powelson supplied titles for others. Powelson often recorded the location and date that he preached each sermon. The bulk of the sermons in the collection were given at the First Congregational Church in Woodbury, Conn. or Tacoma, Wash. Also included is Powelson's original minister's license from the State of Ohio, dated 1875.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Powelson, Alfred Playfair, 1851-1916
First Congregational Church (Tacoma, Wash.)
First Congregational Church (Woodbury, Conn.)
Methodist Church -- Clergy
Methodist Church -- History
Methodist preaching
Sermons
Tacoma (Wash.)--History -- 19th century
United States -- Religion -- 19th century
Woodbury (Conn.)--History -- 19th century
Contents of Collection
- Alfred Playfair Powelson Sermons, 1883-1888, (1 box)
  - Minister's License, State of Ohio, Union County, 1875 October 27 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Sermon preached at: Woodbury, Conn. (1886 December 19); Tacoma, Wash (1888 Jan 15)
  - John 9:13, 1883 (Folder 2)
    Sermon preached at: Woodbury, Conn. (1883)
  - John 17: 9-10., 1883 July 6 (Folder 3)
    Sermon preached at: Woodbury, Conn. (1883 July 6)
  - Matthew I:23., 1883 December (Folder 4)
    Sermon preached at: [?](1883 December 1883); Woodbury, Conn. (1884)
  - John 6:47 - "Verily, truly I say to you he that believe in me haveth eternal life," 1884 January 4 (Folder 5)
    Sermon preached at: Woodbury, Conn. (1884 January 4)
  - John 3:19, 1885 February 15 (Folder 6)
    Sermon preached at: Woodbury, Conn. (1885 February 15)
  - John 20:19, 1885 March 5 (Folder 7)
    Sermon preached at: Woodbury, Conn. (1885 March 5); Tacoma (1888)
  - Psalm 32:5, 1885 April 4 (Folder 8)
    Sermon preached at: Woodbury, Conn. (1885 April 4)
  - Romans 8:14, 1886 January 31 (Folder 9)
    Sermon preached at: Woodbury, Conn. (1886 January 31)
  - Matthew 11:25, 1886 February 7 (Folder 10)
    Sermon preached at: Woodbury, Conn. (1886 February 7)
  - "Obedience", 1886 March 5 (Folder 11)
    Sermon preached at: Woodbury, Conn. (1886 March 5); Tacoma (1887 January 28)
  - Psalm 18:2 - "In Him will I Trust," 1886 May 23 (Folder 12)
    Sermon preached at: Woodbury, Conn. (1886 May 23); [?] (1886 August 29)
  - John 15:22, 1886 July 11 (Folder 13)
    Sermon preached at: Woodbury, Conn. (1886 July 11); Nordbury Church (1886 October 31); Tacoma (1887 June 7)
  - Ezekiel 33:11, 1886 November 21 (Folder 14)
    Sermon preached at: Woodbury, Conn. (1886 November 21)
  - John 1:3 - "Sin Is transgression of law and sin is lawlessness," 1886 December 19 (Folder 15)
    Sermon preached at: Woodbury, Conn. ( 1886 December 19); Tacoma, Wash. (1888 January 16)
  - Luke 2:40, 1886 December 26 (Folder 16)
    Sermon preached at: Woodbury, Conn. (1886 December 26)
  - "Preparatory Lecture", 1886 December 31 (Folder 17)
    Sermon preached at: Woodbury, Conn. (1886 December 31)
  - Luke 15:12, 1887 January 16 (Folder 18)
    Sermon preached at: Woodbury, Conn. (1887 January 16); Tacoma, Wash. (1888 January 29)
  - Phil 4:8, 1888 August 22 (Folder 19)
    Sermon preached at: Woodbury, Conn. (1888 August 22)